<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Otho | Sidenotes</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Otho | Sidenotes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Otho Mantegazza 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Show Absolute and Percent Change in a Time Series</title>
      <link>/post/2019-02-02-butter-consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019-02-02-butter-consumption/</guid>
      <description>1 Load Packages 2 Get the data 3 Wrangle and Estimate Percentage Changes 4 A bit of style 5 Plotting (aka the fun part ;) ) 5.1 Set the basic aesthetic mapping 5.2 Add the first geometric objects 5.3 Specify percent changes explicitly 5.4 Colors colors colors 5.5 Title axis and caption  6 Automate With a Function 7 Waterfall charts   Here I’ll show, you step by step, how to produce the plot in the tweet below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Show Absolute and Percent Change in a Time Series</title>
      <link>/post/2019-02-02-butter.consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019-02-02-butter.consumption/</guid>
      <description>1 Load Packages 2 Get the data 3 Wrangle and Estimate Percentage Changes 4 A bit of style 5 Plotting (aka the fun part ;) ) 5.1 Set the basic aesthetic mapping 5.2 Add the first geometric objects 5.3 Specify percent changes explicitly 5.4 Colors colors colors    Here I’ll show you step by step the plot in the tweet below. In this plot you can show explicitly (and redundantly, but this is not always bad) absolute and relative changes among points in a time series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An analysis of Vera institute&#39;s prison dataset</title>
      <link>/post/2-04-prison/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2-04-prison/</guid>
      <description>1 Intro 2 A strategy for missing values [NA] 2.1 Ignore the NAs 2.2 A more solid strategy  3 Which Category is Overrepresented? 3.1 Exploratory plot 3.2 Hypergeometric test  4 Adjust plot for publication 5 Interpretation and closing remarks   1 Intro This is week 4 of the social data project TidyTuesday. In this week, we explore the incarceration trend dataset. This dataset stores US demographic and incarceration data by county and by gender / ethnic profile for the last 30 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back To The Books</title>
      <link>/post/2017-07-16-back-to-the-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-07-16-back-to-the-books/</guid>
      <description>1 Back To The Books 2 Tools For Writing Open Books on Github 2.1 Markdown 2.2 Git and Github 2.3 Putting it together: Books, authorship and contributions 2.4 Bonus: Bookdown  3 Publishing 3.1 Own website 3.2 Rstudio connect, through Bookdown 3.3 Publishers  4 Impact 4.1 Paywall 4.2 Updates and crowdsourcing  5 Wrapping it up and what’s next   1 Back To The Books Toward the end of my PhD I was struggling to learn new skills such as data analysis and programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fill the Gap</title>
      <link>/post/2017-05-26-fill-the-gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-05-26-fill-the-gap/</guid>
      <description>Can Open Source Hardware help fill the gap and bring technology within reach for everybody?
I am a biologist in academia. I am curious about how Open Source Hardware can improve the way we do research and the way in which we distribute our results and the technology that we produce.
Definitions first The Open Source Hardware Association defines Open Source Hardware as:
 “hardware whose design is made publicly available so that anyone can study, modify, distribute, make, and sell the design or hardware based on that design”</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enabling Tools</title>
      <link>/post/2017-05-16-enabling-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-05-16-enabling-tools/</guid>
      <description>As a young scientist, I find myself facing these challenges (or, at least, let&amp;rsquo;s say that I am trying to improve in these areas):
 make research in an interdisciplinary and distributed context, maximize the chances that anybody can access and reproduce my results, engage with the wide public.  Learning these enabling tools are helping me dealing with this:
 A programming language, easier if it is a high level one such as R or Python.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>